"Reversible Causes
of Premature Hair Graying"
The graying of hair,
the age-related "exhaustion
of the pigmentary potential"
is thought to be mainly genetic,
with a family history
of premature graying
present in up to 90 percent
of cases.
But if the rate of graying
is caused by oxidative damage,
as I described
in the last video,
what role might be played
by antioxidants
and systemic oxidative stress
outside of the hair follicle?
Those with premature graying
do seem to have
higher circulating markers
of oxidative damage
and lower antioxidant levels
in blood.
The higher prevalence of
premature graying among smokers
also supports this possibility
that exogenous free radicals
may speed up the accumulation
of oxidative insults
in the aging hair follicle.
Obese individuals
also tend to gray early,
consistent with
the oxidative stress concept,
though drinkers do not.
Alcohol consumption clearly
causes oxidative stress
yet is not
significantly associated
with premature graying.
Those trying to maximize
their intake of antioxidants
by eating plant-based
must deal with
the Achilles heel-
the risk of
vitamin B12 deficiency
for those not actively
supplementing their diets
with B12,
whether from supplements
or fortified foods.
B12 deficiency is one
of the rare reversible causes
of hair graying through
some unknown mechanism.
Thankfully, hair can repigment
after B12 repletion.
Another reversible cause
is hypothyroidism,
which can be reversed with
thyroid hormone replacement.
Rather than oxidative stress,
what about regular stress?
Does fight-or-flight
turn hair white?
Marie Antoinette syndrome
refers to the rapid graying of
hair due to stress or trauma,
based on the (likely apocryphal)
story of her hair going
completely white
on the eve of her beheading.
Sporadic validated reports
of sudden graying
have been attributed
to the sudden diffuse loss
of pigmented hairs,
leaving the gray hairs behind,
offering the illusion
of transmogrification.
In mice, acute stressors
can lead to hair graying
via rapid depletion
of melanocyte stem cells,
perhaps because
psychological stress
may lead to oxidative stress
(based on cross-sectional
studies that link higher
perceived stress to higher
levels of oxidative DNA damage).
Why might we even have evolved
to turn gray
in response to stress?
Drawing on an analogy
from the authority afforded
silverback mountain gorillas,
stress-induced graying
may confer
a "school of hard knocks"
evolutionary advantage
for leadership.
For real-world consequences,
check out the results
of this study:
hospitalized patients
treated by gray-haired
attending physicians
were found to be
significantly more likely
to make it
out of the hospital alive
than those attended
by dark or blond-haired docs.
As a mark of age, gray hair may
also be a mark of experience.
But might having
gray hair yourself
increase your own chances
of ending up in the hospital?
Might premature
or extensive graying
be a sign of accelerated aging
and subsequent risk
of age-related diseases?
The data is mixed.
Some studies suggest
the degree of graying
is an independent risk factor
for coronary artery disease,
for example based on higher
coronary calcium scores
in grayer individuals.
However,
by far the largest study,
which followed 13,000
men and women for 16 years,
found no correlation
between graying
(or hair loss or wrinkles)
and overall mortality.
The only exception appeared
to be a small fraction of men
without any gray hair
(just 6 percent
of those in their 50s,
2 percent of those in their 60s,
and 1 percent
of those in their 70s),
who did seem to have a
significantly lower mortality.